听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
我想在本节课的最后一部分和大家讨论
In the last bit of this lecture, I want to talk a little bit about
现实中处理故障、构建高可用服务时所面临的问题
a practical real-life context for handling faults and making highly available services.
举例来说 假设你在运行一个在线商店
So, imagine you are running an online shop, for example,
你可能希望商店每周7天、每天24小时都在线
you probably want that shop to be available 24 hours a day, 7 days a week,
谁知道白天或者晚上
because who knows at what time of day or night
会不会有人要看看你的在线商店
somebody might decide that they want to go and look at your shop
买点东西呢
and maybe buy something.
你的商店或服务如果在某些时刻不可用
And so, any time during which your shop, your service is not available
那就会面临收入损失
actually means losing money.
再想象另一个场景
In other cases, you might imagine that
你的服务甚至可能与客户签订了合同
a service may even have contractual relationships with its customers
合同要求你的服务要在多大比例的时间内保证可用性
specifying what percentage of time a service needs to be available.
当我们讨论可用性时 一个典型的模型指标是
And so, a typical model for how we usually talk about availability is
服务可以正确提供功能的时间占比
the fraction of time during which a service is functioning correctly.
举个例子 如果一个服务可以在99%的时间内正确提供功能
And so, if a service is functioning correctly 99% of the time, for example,
这意味着每年服务的不可用时间
that means that there might be 3 to 4 days a year
总计差不多有3到4天
during which the service is not available, in total.
当然了 服务不可用时间的占比还是比较小的
Of course, this might be several smaller outages.
如果你把此指标提高到99.9%
Or if you go up to 99.9% of the time,
则每年服务不可用时间最多不超过9小时
you're allowed a maximum of 9 hours per year of outage.
你可以继续增加9的个数 进一步提高服务的可用性保证
And you can increase this further to as many nines as you like.
例如 电话网络一般会提供5个9的可用性保证
So, the telephone network, for example, is apparently designed for 5 nines.
这个可用性保证指的是老式固定电话网络 不是移动网络
And so, this is the old-fashioned fixed-line telephone network, not mobile networks.
当然也不是指互联网 互联网无法提供如此高的可用性保证
Certainly not the Internet, they don't have this sort of availability.
电话网络使用了非常保守的设计方法
The telephone network is designed in a very conservative way
这才使电话网络可以达到如此高的可靠性
in order to achieve this very high reliability.
但高可用性确实是可实现的
But it is possible.
我们一般还会使用SLO和SLA来定义可用性
And typically, terms that you get in the context of availability is SLO and SLA.
SLO的意思是服务水平目标
So, SLO is Service-Level Objective.
目标是要求你对服务提供具体指标下的可用性保证
It is the goal that you are setting yourself in terms of the availability of a service.
一般是指请求得到正确响应的比例
So, this might specify the percentage of requests that need to get a correct response,
得到正确响应所需的最大响应时间
where the maximum time that it's allowed to take for that response,
例如最大响应时间为200毫秒等
say 200 milliseconds or whatever,
以及在多长时间周期内要保证上述响应指标
and the period of time over which you're going to measure it.
举例来说 你可以将SLO设置为
So, you're going to take that
每天可以正确回复99.9%的请求
99.9% over the cause of all of the requests made in one day, for example.
SLA一般出现在
And then, SLA is basically a contract
服务方与客户或消费者签订的合同中
between a service and its customers or its consumers,
以明确期望达到的服务水平是什么
specifying what the expected service level is.
在分布式系统中 我们一般要构建容错机制
Now, in order to achieve that sort of very high availability,
以保证系统满足所需的高可用性
the way we typically do that in distributed systems is by fault tolerance.
故障是指系统的一部分无法工作
So, a fault is when some part of the system isn't working.
我们这里讨论的节点故障 包含节点本身的崩溃情况
We talked about node faults, which might be a crash, for example,
也包含网络故障 例如出现了网络分区
or network faults, which might be a network partition.
我们希望系统能够容忍一定数量的故障
And what we want is the system to tolerate some number of faults.
让系统容忍所有故障是毫无意义的
So, it doesn't make sense to say that the system will tolerate all faults,
因为如果所有节点都在同一时刻崩溃
because if all of your nodes crash at the same time,
如果所有网络链路都在同一时刻断开
and all of your network links go down at the same time,
系统很显然无法做出任何响应
the system is not going to be able to do anything, obliviously.
没有任何方法可以容忍此类故障
There's no way it can make any progress in that case.
但可以在一定程度上做到容错
But what you might be able to say is that
例如 系统作为整体仍然可以运作的条件是
the system as a whole will continue working
有小于1/2的节点崩溃
if fewer than half of our nodes have crashed, for example.
或有小于1/3的节点崩溃 或有小于2/5的节点崩溃
So, you allow 1/3 to crash, or you allow 2/5 to crash,
剩余节点仍然可以运作 正常对外提供服务
and the remaining nodes can still continue running the service.
当系统中的部分节点或部分网络链路可能出现故障时
And so, in a system in which some nodes or some network links are allowed to be faulty,
我们要避免的是所谓的单点失效
we avoid what is called a single point of failure.
单点失效是指
So, a single point of failure would be say
系统中存在一个节点 如果此节点崩溃 则整个系统都不可用
one node that if that one node crashes, then the system as a whole becomes unavailable.
如果我们可以设计一个不会出现单点失效的系统
But if we can design a system without a single point of failure,
这意味着我们可以移除系统的任何一部分
that means that we can take out any one component of the system,
而系统作为整体仍然可以运作
and the system as a whole will hopefully still continue working.
为了实现容错 我们必须要完成的一项工作是
In order to enable to tolerate faults, usually the first thing we have to do is
检查出故障 能检查出故障才能处理故障
to detect a fault, and then we can handle it.
检查故障的机制叫做失效检查器
So, the mechanism for detecting a fault is known as a failure detector.
这个术语有点奇怪
Terminology is a little bit odd.
更合理的术语应该是故障检查器
It actually should be called a fault detector that would make more sense.
不过失效检查器已经是一个公认的术语了
But a failure detector is the common term that is used.
因此 我这里沿用这一术语
So, we're going to stick with that.
失效检查器可以是一个软件算法
So, a failure detector, it could be like a software algorithm,
也可以是一部分硬件 也可以是其他形式
or it could be a piece of hardware or something,
这是一种检查另一个节点是否出现故障的机制
some mechanism for detecting whether another node is faulty.
理想状态下 我们希望得到的是一个完美失效检查器
And ideally, what we would love to have is a perfect failure detector,
也就是说 这个机制可以准确告知我们
that is, some mechanism that is always accurate at telling us
另一个节点是否出现了故障
whether another node is faulty or not.
我们目前一般使用超时机制来实现失效检查器
Now, the way we typically implement failure detectors is we use timeouts.
我们简单地向节点发送一条消息 消息的内容是
So, we simply send a message to a node, and say,
“如果你还活着 请回复这条消息”
“Hey, please respond to this message if you're alive”.
如果在特定的时间内没有收到任何回复 我们就会说
And then, if we don't get a response within some amount of time, then we say,
“好吧 我没有收到任何回复 那个节点可能已经不在了”
“Well, OK, we didn't get a response. That node must be dead”.
“那个节点一定是崩溃了 或者发生了其他什么事情”
“So, it must have crashed or something like that”.
这个机制效果很好 也很实用
And this is fine. This is practical.
但不幸的是 正如我们在系统模型部分见到的那样
But unfortunately, as we have seen in the context of our system models,
如果我们假设的是一个部分同步系统 甚至假设的是一个异步系统
if we assume a partially synchronous or even an asynchronous system,
则超时并不能准确告诉我们某个节点是否崩溃了
then a timeout doesn't necessarily tell us that the node has crashed,
因为非同步系统自身也可能出现超时的情况
because then timeout could also happen,
当我们在此类系统中发送一条消息时 此消息可能会在网络中丢失
because we sent a message, and the message was lost in the network,
响应消息也可能会在网络中丢失
or the response was lost in the network,
消息的传输可能会出现网络延迟
or the message was delayed in the network,
消息虽然最终仍然能到达目的地 只是一定时间内还没到达
and it will actually still arrive, it just hasn't arrived yet,
响应的传输也可能会出现网络延迟
or the response was delayed in the network,
节点有可能还活着
or maybe the node is actually alive,
但是节点处于暂停状态 正在执行较长时间的垃圾回收
but it's just experiencing a long garbage collection pause,
节点可能需要完成垃圾回收后才能响应消息
and so, it will respond to your message in one minute's time
可能需要过一分钟才会响应消息
once it's finished its garbage collection,
当然了 节点也有可能真的崩溃了
or of course, the note might have crashed.
节点可能发生上述所有情况 超时机制无法区分出节点具体发生了什么
And it's impossible to tell the difference between any of these.
因此 发送检查消息的发送方不可能获知
So, it's impossible for the sender of these check messages to tell
没有收到响应的原因到底是由网络问题导致的
whether the absence of a response is due to a network problem
还是由某种随机延迟导致的
or due to just some kind of random delay,
还是真的因为节点已经崩溃才无法收到响应的
or due to problems because the node is actually crashed.
我们可以构建出完美失效检查器的条件是
Now, we can build a perfect failure detector
我们使用同步系统模型
if we have a synchronous system model,
且我们只假设存在崩溃停止节点
and if we're going to assume only crash-stop failures,
假设系统中的节点不会出现任何拜占庭行为
and certainly not going to assume any Byzantine behavior in the system.
但只要切换到部分同步模型
But as soon as you go to a partially synchronous model,
则超时机制就无法准确检测出故障了
then timeouts are no longer an exact way of detecting failures.
在部分同步网络系统中 我们能实现的最佳效果是
So, the best we can do in a partially synchronous system is what is called
最终完美失效检查器
an eventually perfect failure detector.
我很喜欢这个术语 没有人是完美的
I love this term. Nobody is perfect.
我认为我最终能做到完美 可能大家也能最终变得完美
I like to think of myself as eventually perfect. Maybe you are also eventually perfect.
在失效检查器场景下 最终完美的意思是
And then, in the context of a failure detector, eventually perfect means that
失效检查器可能在某个时刻内犯错
the failure detector might be wrong from time to time.
失效检查器有时虽然检查到了超时情况
So, the failure detector might detect a timeout
但此时节点可能并没有崩溃
even though the other node hasn't actually crashed yet,
只是因为消息传输出现了一点延迟
just because a message happened to be delayed a bit.
这意味着 应用超时机制无法准确指出节点是否已经崩溃
So, it means a timeout does not accurately indicate that a crash has happened.
失效检查器无法立即得到真实的检查结果
Also, a failure detector is not immediate.
如果节点已经崩溃 需要花费一定的时间才能检查到真的出现了崩溃
So, if a crash has happened, it might actually take a while until we detect that crash.
崩溃检查并不是瞬时完成的
The detection of the crash is not instantaneous.
我们可能会犯错
So, we might be wrong.
我们在一定时间内可能会出现误报或漏报
We might have both false positives and false negatives for a while.
但最终我们总能做到
But eventually,
当且仅当节点崩溃时 失效检查器将此节点标记为崩溃
the failure detector labels a node as crashed if and only if it really has crashed.
这意味着临时怀疑另一个节点出现故障的情况最终会被纠正
So, that means that any temporarily suspecting another node of being failed will stop.
我们能重新将某个节点标记为正确节点
And we'll go back to thinking that a node is correct
当然了 前提是这确实还是一个正确节点
provided that the node really is still correct.
如果一个节点出现故障 我们最终可以检查到确实出现了故障
And also, if a node has failed, then eventually we will detect it as failed.
这就是故障检查我们能做到的最好效果了
And so, this is about the best we can do in terms of failure detection.
但即使做到这样也很不错
But it's still quite useful.
即使失效检查器仅能做到最终完美
So, even though we might have this failure detector that is only eventually perfect,
对于构建一些可用的算法来说也已经足够了
this is actually sufficient in order to build some useful algorithms
我们后面会具体展开讨论
as we will see in some of the future lectures.
这就是今天有关系统模型的全部内容了
So, that's all for today on system models.